Inventory to the Jean Wittenberg Collection, 1940-1945
Hoover Institution Archives
Jean Wittenberg Collection,
1940-1945
XX020
Wittenberg, Jean, collector
3 manuscript boxes 1.25 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Pamphlets and serial issues, clandestinely issued in German-occupied Belgium during World War II, relating to the Belgian resistance movement
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Belgium; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements; Belgium; Belgium--History--German occupation, 1940-1945
Introduction to the Jean Wittenberg Collection
In 1944, shortly after the liberation of Brussels, an exhibition of the Belgian clandestine press was organized at La Maison du Peuple de Schaerbeek, a suburb of Brussels. The Maison du Peuple is commonly known as the seat of the socialist party. The exhibits were chiefly made up with clandestine periodicals circulated during the occupation by the leftish elements. I noticed at that time that the most important contribution to the exhibition originated from a certain Jean WITTENBERG, a socialist propagandist.
I succeeded in getting in touch with Mr. Wittenberg and was allowed to investigate his collection which was grouping as much as 71 different clandestine periodicals. Mr. Wittenberg finally agreed to sell his entire collection to the Hoover War Library for Belgian Francs 10.000.- viz about $230.
Mr. Wittenberg's personality is quite fascinating: In December 1940 he was already selling 14 different clandestine papers. He was arrested in January 1942, tortured and jailed by the Gestapo. Six months afterwards, he was liberated owing to lack of evidence. He soon resumed his clandestine activity and did not hesitate to hide two Jewish children in his Brussels home. But in June 1944 he was again arrested and sent to a concentration camp in Northern France from where he escaped on August 3rd.
More detailed information on Jean Wittenberg and his war adventures may be found in this file, viz: two articles of the Belgian daily paper Le Peuple Oct. 13 and 14, 1944, and a few pages of personal memoirs Jean Wittenberg wrote at my request.
Jean Wittenberg being a socialist propagandist his collection is exceptionally rich in pamphlets, cartoons, periodicals circulated during the German occupation by the leftish elements:
To consult the collection, please use the inventory prepared by Jean Wittenberg himself.
The periodicals have been grouped according to political tendencies and not according to alphabetical order.
The figures in red pencil match with the figures labeled on each file.
Preliminary Inventory
- 1 Parti socialiste belge.
  - Journaux:
    - 1. Peuple: 1-2 - déc.41-janv.1942 - févr.42 - avr.42 - mai 42 - Juin 42 - déc. 42 - janv.43 - mars 43 - avr.43 - mai 43 - déc. 43 - mai 44 - sept. 44 - Éte 44
    - 2. Espoir: avr. 41 - oct.41 - nov.41 - déc.41 - janv. 42 - mai 42 - juin 43 - jenv. 44
    - 3. Le Monde du Travail: 4 sans date - déc.42 - mai 42 - mai 42 - févr.42 - août 43 - juin 44
    - 4. Jeunesse nouvelle: juin 43 - juill.43 - oct.43 - janv.44
    - 5. Combat: janv. 44 - mars 44
  - 2 Divers: feuille avec empreintes des soeaux employés pour la confection des faux papiers
    - Feuille avec faux timbre de ravitoillement
  - 3 Brochures: Le sourire occulté.
    - Contribution à l'histoire de guerre
    - De la capitulation à la trahison
    - Statuts du P.O.B.
    - Notre programme d'action immédiat
  - 4 Caricatures: 2
  - 5 Tracts: Vive le socialisme.
    - Lettre ouverte à MM. les Bourgmestres
    - A la population belge
    - A bas les déportations
    - Comité d'action des étudiants socialistes
    - ler mai 1943
    - ler mai 1944
    - Aux cultivateurs et fermiers
  - 6 Etudes socialistes: Idée socialiste
    - Doctrine et parti
    - La guerre et nous
    - Le guide du militant
  - 7 Solidarité: Promotion Emile Vandervelde
    - Photo Vandervelde
    - Photo De Brouckère
  - 8 Syndicat:
  - Journaux:
    - 6. Vaincre: Nos. 1-2-6-8-10
  - 9 Tracts: Appel
    - Syndicat général service public
    - Confédération générale syndicats libres de Belgique
    - Mots d'ordre syndicaux
    - C.G.T.B.
    - Libérons le travail
    - Vers la délivrance
  - 10 Journaux socialistes flamands:
    - 7. De Werker: juin 43 - déc.43 - janv.44
    - 8. Morgenrood: janv.42 - sept.43
  - 11 Service "Mandrille" pour la démoralisation des troupes allemandes: 2 paquets de tracts
    - 8 tracts rédigés en allemand et parachutés pour notre service
- 12 Parti communiste belge.
  - Journaux:
    - 9. Le Drapeau Rouge: Déc.41 - févr.42 - mars 42 - févr.43 - mai 44 - ler juin 44 - 10 juin 44 - 30 juin 44 - 7 août 44
    - 10. Clarté: avr.41 - mars 41 - août 44
    - 11. De Roode Vaan: Déc.41 - aug.43 - juin 44
    - 12. Strijd: 21 Juli 44
  - Brochures: L'Internationale
    - Le Pillage du Pays
    - Le vrai visage de l'Union Soviétique
    - De Waarheid over de U.R.S.S.
    - Le parti communiste a 20 ans.
  - Tracts: ler mai
    - Divers 3
    - ler mai 1948
    - Réponse à l'arme secrète allemande
    - Métallurgistes bruxellois
    - L'Allemagne, etc.
  - Les Amis de l'U.R.S.S.
  - Journaux:
    - 13. Radio Moscou: 14 fév.43 - 21 févr.43 - 30 mai 44
- 13 Front de l'Indépendance:
  - Journaux:
    - 14. Front français: Noël 43 - 5 juin 44 - 17 juin 44 - 5 juill.44 - 21 août 44
    - 15. Front flamand: août 44
    - 16. Libération du Brabant: 12-14-16-17
    - 17. Libération, Flandre wallonne: 10 mai 43 -4-7-8
    - 18. Libération, région Ouest Hainaut: 1-2-3-4
    - 19. Indépendance: n° 11
    - 20. Médecine libre: n° 2
    - 21. Vengeons nos martyrs: 1-2-3
    - 22. Bulletin intérieur:n° 25
    - 23. La Polioier libre: 1
    - 24. La résistance: 36-37-38-39-41
    - 25. L'Elastique: n° 1
    - 26. Le Soir (counterfeit of Nazi papers)
    - 27. Signal. (counterfeit of Nazi papers)
    - 28. Terre at Nation (counterfeit of Nazi papers)
  - 14 Solidarité: Photo:- avion - Bateau - Roosevelt Staline et Churchill - Bertulot Fraiteur Raskin - Fraiteur - Léopold Marcq - Edmond Eycken - Liénart Jules - Honoré Willems - Amédée Ballegeer
    - Ticket Croix Rouge: 2 fr. 5 fr. 10 fr.
    - Cernet de 250 fr.
    - Carnet Adama
    - Rapport d'activité
    - Bulletin intérieur: juin 44 - juill.44 - août 44
    - Bulletin intérieur flamand: févr.44
  - 15 Tracts: Officiers d'active, etc.
    - Concitoyens
    - Manifeste
    - Nous accusons l'occupant
- 16 Mouvement national belge
  - Journaux:
    - 29. La Voix des Belges: 5-6-8-9-11-12-13-27-28-31-32-35-36-37
  - Tracts: Belges, souvenez-vous des traitres
    - Souvenir du 10 mai 1942
- 17 La Libre Belgique:
  - 30. Journaux: 2-12-15-16-20B-22-22 différent-26-31-33-40-43-44-48-49-51-54-58-59-60-61-64-65-66-68-69-70-71-74-75-76-77-78 et 79-80-81-85
- 18 Het Vrije Woord:
  - Journaux:
    - 31. Het vrije woord: 1-6-11-12-14-15-17-19-26-29-31
    - 32. Das Freie Wort: 3-6-7-8-9
- 19 Les Allemands libres de Belgique:
  - Journaux:
    - 33. Die Wahrheit (10)
  - Tracts: Déposer les armes
    - Manifeste Comité National de l'Allemagne libre
    - Appel du Général Walter von Seidlitz
    - 20 tracts rédigés en allemand destinés aux troupes
- Les Autrichiens libres en Belgique.
  - Journaux:
    - 34. Freies Osterreich: 4
  - Tracts: 5 tracts rédigés en allemand destinés aux troupes
- 20 Journaux divers
  - 35. La Légion noire. n° 6 - janv.1944
  - 36. Churchill Gazette
  - 37. Le Hérisson
  - 38. La Belgique indépendante. N° 11
  - 39. Ça ira
  - 40. Contre attaque
  - 41. La Voix de Lénine févr.44 - mars 44
  - 42. Le réveil des mineurs
  - 43. La Victoire
  - 44. La Wallonie libre
  - 45. La Wallonie indépendante: 3-4-5-7
  - 46. De Vrijschutter
  - 47. Vrij
  - 48. De Eenheid
  - 49. Klassenstrijd
  - 50. Liberté: 2-3-4-5-6-8-13
  - 51. La Liberté
  - 52. Le Roi, la loi, la Liberté: 10-11
  - 53. L'Insoumis: 31-34-37-39-40-41
  - 54. Vérités Truth: Le Roi Albert: 9-10-40-42
  - 55. Chut: 70-72-74-75-76-77
  - 56. Sous la botte: 14-15-16-17
  - 57. La libre Belgique illustrée: 1-2-5-6-7-8-10-11
  - 58. Combattre: 18-19-20-21-22-23
  - 59. Le Partisan: sept.43-23-24
  - 60. De Partisaan: 15-2 n° 20-24
  - 61. Le Belge: 11-73
- 21 Faux Papiers:
  - Cartes d'Identité: Mouscron - Lessines - Jeneffe-en-Condroz - Achet - Genval - Mons - Koekelberg - Anderlecht - Bruxelles 2 modèles
    - Carte d'identité de la police anxiliaire
    - Carte d'identité d'étranger
    - Carte de ravitaillement (jaune)
    - Abonnement chemin de fer
  - Cartes de légitimation: Ministère de I'Intérieur et de la Santé Publique, 3 modèles
    - Ville de Bruxelles Ministère des Communications.3.modèles
    - Nationale Maatschappij van Buurtspoorwegen
    - Societé Nationale des chemins de fer Vicinaux
    - Ministerie van Openbare Werken
    - Carte de travail
    - Théâtre de la Lonnaie
    - Certificat de travail
    - Rijksarbeidsambt
    - Administration des services de contrôle: Commission:
    - Bescheinigung
    - Berechtigungsschein
    - Police: titre de congé
    - Police: autorisation de porter la tenue civile
    - Photo des sceaux (faux) en usage à la police de Bruxelles
    - Empreintes de faux cachets 5 feuilles
  - 22 Divers:
    - Proclamation de M. Van de Meulebroeck, original français et flamand
    - Organisation de faux depart en Angleterre 3 feuilles
    - Emission de la B.B.C. pour la presse clandestine
  - 23 La Déportation: Copie de la lettre de la Cour de Cassation
    - Copie de la lattre de l'Archevêché d'Utrecht
    - Copie lettre adressée par le Secrétsire Général Plisnier à son collègue M. Verwilghen
    - Uberweisungsschein N° 4
    - Dienstverichtungsbescheid
    - Copie lettre de l'Association des étudiants au Général Von Falkenhausen
    - Copie de la lettre du Roi au Président de la Croix Rouge de Belgique
    - 24 Menace rexiste aux intellectuels
    - Les origines juives de Léon Degrelle
    - Copie de la protestation du Cardinal Van Roey contre l'enlévement des cloches
    - Conférence de Raymond de Becker
    - Copie de lettre de condemnes à mort
  - 25 Brochures: La Belgique loyale
    - La vraie Belgique (réponse à la Belgique loyale)
    - Brochure en faveur du Roi Léopold III en flamand
- 26 Divers parachutés par la R.A.F.
  - Journaux:
    - 62. The Times: 6 (miniature)
    - 63. The Daily Telegraph
    - 64. L'Arc en Ciel: 1-2-3-4-5-6-7-8-16-20-22
  - 27 Brochures parachutées par la R.A.F.: De Wereldwind
    - Beroepsgeheimen
    - Conseils pratiques pour la lutte contre le Doryphore
    - Imprènable
    - Tours de mains
    - La guerre en dentelles
    - Journal illustré
    - Société Nationale des Chemins de fer
  - 28 Tracts: R.A.F. 3 vignettes
    - Avertissement peuple belge
    - Discours de M. Eden
    - Tracts divers 23
  - 29 Clichés: pour la presse clandestine avec comment.et mode d'emploi
  - Journaux:
    - 65. De Luchtpost: 6-8-9-11
    - 66. Le courrier de l'air: 5-12-21-21-24 nov.42-suppl.-14-3-43-3-6-43-16-7-43-10-2- 44-16-3-44-23-3-44-30-3-44-3-4-44
  - 30 67. Revue de la Presse Libre: 8-12-13-45
    - 68. Tous les Fronts: 29-8-44
  - Brochures: La Revue du Monde libre
    - La France libre: 1-1-2-3-4
  - Tracts: 6
- 31 Journaux et Tracts destinés aux Boches.
  - Journaux:
    - 69. Luftpost n° 8
    - 70. Sternenbanner: 14-3-44 - 28-3-44
  - Brochures: 2
  - Tracts: 15
- 32 Amerique.
  - Journaux:
    - 71. L'Amerique en guerre: 42-78S-83-84-85-90-93-95-96-97-98-99
  - Tracts: 5
- 71 Journaux différents.
  - 33 Brochures: Degrelle, Leon, un nouveau plan pour la collaboration
  - von Bissing Godefroid de Bouillon
  - Tracts. 3